### Maria Melnikova

- Software Engineer-

mariiamelnikova96@gmail.com | (253)224-6240 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/mariia-mel/ | https://github.com/mariiamel | https://mariia-portfolio.herokuapp.com/

#### Overview

I'm a Software Developer with a unique background in customer service & collaborative work experience, which sharpened my leadership and management skills, especially in high-stress situations, and helped to established and maintained productive consistent working relationships with the team. I am passionate about creating tangible solutions that make an impact on those around me and love to learn and share my knowledge with others.

#### Skills

- Languages, Frameworks, and Technologies: JavaScript (ES6), Typescript, Python, HTML, CSS, React, NPM, Node.js, Express.js, Bootstrap, EJS, JSX, REST, APIs, Axios, JWT, Command Line (CLI), Git, GitHub
- Databases: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Sequelize

#### **Software Engineering Projects**

**Trip Tracker | Full- Stack Web Application** (MERN Stack App allowing users to stay organized while traveling)- *March 2021* **Tech**: React, JavaScript, Node.js, Express.js, Mongoose, MongoDB, Bcrypt, Axios, JWT, HTML and CSS

- Worked with a group of 4 to perform a full-stack app and manage project scope, using Git collaboration
- Dynamically integrated asynchronous Axios API calls with minimization efforts to reduce latency and increase the app's speed and overall smoothness by 15%
- Enabled user login with hashed encryption, employing RESTful routing to maintain trip planning details
- Implemented in-depth schema in Mongo

**CoffeeMe | Full-Stack Web Application** (Search for the coffeeshops and add them to your list of favorites)- *February 2021* **Tech**: JavaScript, EJS, Sequelize, Postgres, Express.js, Node.js, API, Axios

- Coded a user login system, storing encrypted information in cookies and SQL, to allow custom user experiences based on preferences while maintaining user privacy
- Optimized pages for the loading speed under 3 sec
- Exported data from APIs to SQL database utilizing JavaScript and EJS to render searched coffeeshops to maximize readability and overall usability
- Implemented the entire site through Sequelize, following full RESTful routing, giving the user access to full CRUD functionality on the site

Guess Where | Front-End Web Game (Challenge yourself to see if you can guess where the item is hidden)- February 2021

<u>Tech</u>: Javascript, HTML, CSS(Flexbox), and DOM manipulation in one week with functional JavaScript logic that allows a user to guess its attributes against a computer opponent

 Built unique Front-end web applications Javascript functionality to keep track of user's level, attempts, items to guess that is based on real value

# **Professional Experience**

Freelance Frontend Software Engineer | (05/2020 – present Greater Seattle Area, WA, United States) Design and develop HTML, CSS, JS, React.js for a variety of micro sites and landing pages. Use Ajax Requests, REST API for obtaining data which was in JSON format.

Patient Care Coordinator | Advanced Foot and Ankle Clinic (02/2020 – 01/2021 Bellevue, United States)

Critically analyzed and reviewed annual patient charts to ensure 100% accuracy every week. Checked in and scheduled future appointments with patients. Made insurance calls to follow up on medical claims.

**Shift Manager** | *Gebr. Heinemann* (07/2018 – 11/2019 Yekaterinburg, Russia)

Introduced new templates for reporting documentation on revenue and sales for each shift, which saved admin staff an average of 1 hour per day. Supervised and trained staff of 10-15 employees, enabling them to improve soft skills, achieve daily objectives, and deliver high-quality services.

#### Education

#### Harvard University, CS50's Introduction to Computer Science (05/2021 – 08/2021)

A broad and robust understanding of computer science, programming, and security. How to think algorithmically and solve programming problems efficiently. Related studies in Scratch, C, Arrays, Algorithms, Memory, Data Structures, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.

General Assembly, Software Engineering Immersive (01/2021 – 04/2021 Seattle, WA)

Software Engineering Immersive student in a rigorous, 12-week, 450+ hour program aimed at building technology industry skills for the development of consistent full-stack and Front-end web applications with JavaScript, React, Express, Node, and SQL as well as proving an in-depth understanding of Software Development best practices and technologies, computer science fundamentals, algorithms and data structures through project development (collaboration with the team and solo).

**Bachelor's degree** (09/2014 – 08/2018 Yekaterinburg, Russia) Ural State Pedagogical University
Field of study - International Relations and Affairs.
Diploma with Honors

## Leadership skills and Volunteer experience

### WomenTech Ambassador & Influencer (March 2021 – Present)

Develop leadership skills and expand the network participating in events. Take initiative and constantly invite talented women to the community.

### FIFA World Cup 2018 (Russia)

Organized an entertainment program which helped to involve more fans by 35%. Communicated effectively with volunteers' team of 100-110 people.

### **Spoken Languages:**

- English (fluent)
- Russian (native)